A Guide to the Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Armstrong Chaloner
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-394-e
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift to the Library from George Worthington, Charlottesville, Va., on May 24, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Armstrong Chaloner [Chanler] of Merrie Mills, Charlottesville, Virginia (1862-1935) was the great-great grandson of John Jacob Astor and for a short time was married to Amélie Rives (1863-1945) who was an American novelist who lived at Castle Hill, Charlottesville, Virginia. They were married in 1888 and divorced in 1895. It has been written that "Amélie was a master manipulator and morphine addict who refused her besotted husband sex and affection while spending his inheritance to refurbish her family plantation." Amélie is described as very flirtatious but her real passion seems to have been for Castle Hill and she desperately needed money to maintain her beloved home.
Chaloner's parents died when he was young leaving him to be the head of his family. He ran a business called the Roanoke Rapids Machine Shops but as his ideas for its expansion grew, his siblings feared they were going to lose money on it. This coupled with his neglect for his siblings (due to tensions between them and Amélie Rives) motivated the sibling to have Chaloner committed to an insane asylum. The couple's divorce after seven years was fodder for the media as were Chaloner's commitment to the asylum, his escape four years later and his lawsuits to prove his sanity and reclaim his fortune. Following their divorce Amélie Rives married Pierre Troubetsky and Chaloner still sent her money. After his escape from Bloomingdale and following the success of his trial, he returned to his home, Merrie Mills. In addition to being an author of several books, he wrote long passages about experiencing trance like states where he could see other realms of existence. He discussed these trances and his interest in psychology with important authors such as Henry James.
Scope and Content
The papers consist of 147 letters and documents (1894-1920) by and to John Armstrong Chaloner (1862-1935), great-great grandson of John Jacob Astor of New York. Chaloner was an attorney, novelist, and entrepreneur who was often described as an eccentric. He lived at Castle Hill, and Merrie Mills Farm in Albemarle County, Virginia and owned a mill in Roanoke Rapids in North Carolina.
The collection includes letters from various friends and business associates regarding financial help and business matters about his mill. There are also letters about Chaloner's escape from an insane asylum; letters to Judge Thomas N. Hill about his legal insanity case; letters to his friend, Rose Wilmer Page, asking for help with his lawsuit; a petition for a temporary injunction in Chaloner v. Dunn before the Supreme Court; and a certificate indicating a transfer of ownership of four cattle. There is also a document written by Chaloner stating that in the event of his death, he did not want his siblings on his property except for the viewing.
There are letters from J. Marion Lee, who had been involuntarily committed to the Manhattan State Hospital, and was writing to her acquaintances asking for help in proving her sanity and receiving authorization for her release. She mentioned that she had a relationship in 1894 with Dr. James Albert "Al" Meara who allegedly drugged her, robbed her and had her committed because she had found out information about him that he wanted kept secret. There are love letters from Dr. Meara written to Miss Lee included in the collection. Her letters give a horrifying glimpse into incarceration in an insane asylum from 1894 to 1901.
There are also letters from Albert and Abbie Legg asking Chaloner for money. Albert Legg was a former employee of Mr. Chaloner who wrote complaining about his wife and needing money. There are also letters from Abbie Legg who claimed that her husband mistreated her and left her penniless. Included with their correspondence is a letter from a policeman in Knoxville, Tennessee about Legg's drunkenness and womanizing. Chaloner wrote to Abbie Legg offering money to her husband on the condition that Legg would give some of it to her.
There is correspondence between Mary Stacha Young and John Armstrong Chaloner that reveal that she was a singer who was in and out of work and had to support herself and her mother. She wrote to Mr. Chaloner telling him about her despair and requesting financial assistance. Chaloner responded that he would help them once he regained his rights to his property from his legal case. There is also correspondence about Chaloner's book, The X-Faculty and his experiences with psychic phenomena.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically for correspondence and within each folder.
Contents List
- Certificate of Record for the American Jersey Cattle Club 1912 April 1 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Correspondence: Letters of J. Marion Lee at the Manhattan Mental Hospital 1894-1901, 20 items (Box-folder 1:2)
  Love letters from Dr. James Albert "Al" Meara to Marion Lee; and letters from Marion Lee to Mrs. Adaline E. Jackson, Mrs. Addie Eldridge, George Gordon Battle, Mrs. W. A. Hersey, Dr. H. B. Brice, and John Armstrong Chaloner
- Correspondence: Albert Legg, Abbie Legg and John Armstrong Chaloner 1902-1903, 10 items (Box-folder 1;3)
  June 25, n. y. Albert Legg: "The devil has taken hold of Mrs. Legg again and she is keeping me in hot water all of the time."
  December 28, 1903 John Armstrong Chaloner writes to Abbie Legg that when his case is settled he will pay Mr. Legg one hundred dollars a month on the condition that Albert would give her thirty dollars a month.
- Correspondence: Letters to John Armstrong Chaloner 1901-1904, 7 items (Box-folder 1:4)
  Correspondents include Effie Ruth Varney (requests his autograph), Mary Elizabeth Breen (wishes him congratulations on his escape from Bloomingdale and success with his new book), George F. Fitzgerald, G. W. Vincent, John Penn Morris, and Laura Powers from the Methodist Church (requesting an organ for the church.)
- 5 Correspondence: Mary Stacha Young and John Armstrong Chaloner 1903-1904, 5 items (Box-folder 1:5)
- Correspondence John Armstrong Chaloner to Thomas N. Hill 1905, 3 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
  There are letters asking Judge Hill to write a letter in support of Chaloner to Judge James U. Osborne regarding Chaloner's insanity case.
- Correspondence: John Armstrong Chaloner to "Whom it may concern" 1909, 1 item. (Box-folder 1:7)
  In the event of his death Chaloner does not want his siblings on his property.
- Correspondence: John Armstrong Chaloner to Mr. G. B. Rives 1911, 2 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Letters from John Armstrong Chaloner about using the pathway located on the property of Mr. Rives and regarding typhoid and the condition of Mrs. Douglas [wife of the groundskeeper.]
- Correspondence: Rose Wilmer Page and John Armstrong Chaloner 1904, 1910, 12 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Correspondence: Rose Wilmer Page and John Armstrong Chaloner 1911, 15 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Business Correspondence 1901-1905; 1911, 27 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
  There are letters between F. H. Treacy and John Armstrong Chaloner about the leasing or sale of the Roanoke Rapids Machinery Shop. Other correspondents mentioned are H. V. N. Philip, Winthrop Astor Chanler, Stanford White, and James Lindsay Gordon. Other business correspondence includes information about selling puppies, the Keswick Country Club, membership in the Alliance Francaise and a letter from the United States Patent Office regarding Chaloner's "Quarterly Newspaper." Correspondents in these matters were Emma K. Griffith, Richard H. Wilson, and H. E. Magruder.
- Psychical Correspondence 1901-1911, 6 items (Box-folder 1:12)
  Correspondence includes a letter from J. H. Hyslop to Chaloner asking for twenty five thousand to start the American Society for Psychical Research. Correspondents who admired Chaloner's writings on psychic phenomenon included Joseph Jalrow, Mrs. Joel W. Giles and Annie de Beers.
- Publisher Correspondence 1901; 1904, 3 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
  October 1901 letter regarding advice on the paper and binding for Chaloner's book. Includes an untitled manuscript fragment/story about[Seraphine and Malatesta?]
- Invitations 1903-1904, 5 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
  November 29, 1904 invitation from Edwin A. Alderman to meet the French ambassador.
- News clippings, 15 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
  There are newspaper clippings about a District Attorney arraigning public officials and the "newspaper government;" a clipping about the murder of McAuliffe; news about the Boer War; and various news clippings mentioning members of the Astor family.
- Petition for temporary injunction in Chaloner v. Dunn 1921, 1 item, printed. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Supreme Court Case; notice of motion about the citizenship (Virginia or North Carolina) of John Armstrong Chaloner.
- Printed materials, 5 items (Box-folder 1:17)
- Receipts 1901, 9 items. (Box-folder 1:18)